# **Gabriel Lima**

gabriel.lima@kaist.ac.kr·+82-10-7280-7236 https://thegcamilo.github.io/·@gcamilo\_lima

Data Science Group, Institute for Basic Science, 55 Expo-ro, Yuseong-gu, Daejeon, South Korea, 34126

Last Updated: February, 2022

### **RESEARCH INTERESTS**

I am a computer scientist interested in understanding people's perception of artificial intelligence (AI) systems and how they will morally and legally affect society. I address these research questions through the lens of moral and legal responsibility, and I investigate the possible conflicts between the regulation and development of machines and the public view of these new technologies. My research aims to study how people perceive the moral agency and patiency of AI systems to embed their opinion in normative research and policymaking.

### **EDUCATION**

# Korea Advanced Institute of Science and Technology (KAIST)

Daejeon, South Korea, Mar. 2021 - Present

M.S. in Computer Science. Advisor: Meeyoung Cha.

# Korea Advanced Institute of Science and Technology (KAIST)

Daejeon, South Korea, Feb. 2017 - Feb. 2021

Advanced B.S. in Computer Science (with honors).

# École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne (EPFL)

Lausanne, Switzerland, Sep. 2019 - Feb. 2020

Exchange Semester at the School of Computer and Communication Sciences.

# **JOURNAL PAPERS**

Karandeep Singh\*, **Gabriel Lima**\*, Meeyoung Cha, Chiyoung Cha, Juhi Kulshrestha, Yong-Yeol Ahn, Onur Varol. "Misinformation, Believability, and Vaccine Acceptance Over 40 Countries: Takeaways From the Initial Phase of The COVID-19 Infodemic." *PLOS ONE*. 2022 (\* denotes co-first authorship). https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0263381

Saifeldeen Zihiri\*, **Gabriel Lima**\*, Jiyoung Han, Meeyoung Cha, Wonjae Lee. "QAnon Shifts Into the Mainstream, Remains a Far-Right Ally." *Heliyon*. 2022 (\* denotes co-first authorship). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2022.e08764

**Gabriel Lima**, Meeyoung Cha, Chihyung Jeon, Kyung Sin Park. "The Conflict Between People's Urge to Punish Al and Legal Systems." *Frontiers in Robotics and Al*. 2021. https://doi.org/10.3389/frobt.2021.756242

**Gabriel Lima**, Assem Zhunis, Lev Manovich, Meeyoung Cha. "On the Social-Relational Moral Standing of AI: An Empirical Study Using AI-Generated Art." *Frontiers in Robotics and AI*. 2021. https://doi.org/10.3389/frobt.2021.719944

Meeyoung Cha, Chiyoung Cha, Karandeep Singh, **Gabriel Lima**, Yong-Yeol Ahn, Juhi Kulshrestha, Onur Varol. "Prevalence of Misinformation and Factchecks on the COVID-19 Pandemic in 35 Countries: Observational Infodemiology Study." *JMIR Human Factors*. 2021.

https://doi.org/10.2196/23279

**Gabriel Lima**, Meeyoung Cha, Chiyoung Cha, Hyeyoung Hwang. "COVID-19 Vaccine Acceptance in the US and UK in the Early Phase of the Pandemic: Al-Generated Vaccines Hesitancy for Minors, and the Role of Governments." *Journal of the Korean Data Analysis Society.* 2021.

http://doi.org/10.37727/jkdas.2021.23.3.1043

# **CONFERENCE PAPERS**

**Gabriel Lima**, Jiyoung Han, Meeyoung Cha. "Others Are to Blame: A Multi-Faceted View on Whom People Consider Responsible For Online Misinformation." *Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW)*. 2022.

https://doi.org/10.1145/3512953

Assem Zhunis, **Gabriel Lima**, Hyeonho Song, Jiyoung Han, Meeyoung Cha. "Emotion Bubbles: Emotional Compositions of Online Discourse Before and After the COVID-19 Outbreak." *Proceedings of the Web Conference (WebConf)*. 2022.

https://doi.org/10.1145/3485447.3512132

**Gabriel Lima**, Nina Grgić-Hlača, Meeyoung Cha. "Human Perceptions on Moral Responsibility of AI: A Case Study in AI-Assisted Bail Decision-Making." *Proceedings of the CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems*. 2021.

https://doi.org/10.1145/3411764.3445260

**Gabriel Lima**, Changyeon Kim, Seungho Ryu, Chihyung Jeon, Meeyoung Cha. "Collecting the Public Perception of Al and Robot Rights." *Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW)*. 2020.

https://doi.org/10.1145/3415206

**Gabriel Lima**, Chihyung Jeon, Meeyoung Cha, Kyungsin Park. "Will Punishing Robots Become Imperative in the Future?." Extended Abstracts of the CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. 2020. https://doi.org/10.1145/3334480.3383006

**Gabriel Lima**, Sungkyu Park, Meeyoung Cha. "Robots for Class President: Children's Positions Toward AI Robot Rights." *Proceedings of the Korea Computer Congress (KCC)*. 2019.

**Gabriel Lima**, Jin Yeong Bak. "Speech Emotion Classification using Raw Audio Input and Transcriptions." *Proceedings of the 2018 International Conference on Signal Processing and Machine Learning*. 2018. https://doi.org/10.1145/3297067.3297089

# **WORKSHOP PAPERS**

**Gabriel Lima**, Meeyoung Cha. "Descriptive AI Ethics: Collecting and Understanding the Public Opinion." Ethics in Design Workshop at the ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW). 2020.

https://arxiv.org/abs/2101.05957

**Gabriel Lima**, Meeyoung Cha. "Responsible AI and Its Stakeholders." Fair and Responsible AI Workshop at 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. 2020. https://arxiv.org/abs/2004.11434

# **WORK EXPERIENCES**

#### School of Humanities & Social Sciences, KAIST

Daejeon, South Korea, Aug. 2021 - Dec, 2021

Teaching Assistant of the Scientific Writing class (CC500). Responsible for grading students' research papers and assisting with administrative tasks.

# School of Computing, KAIST

Daejeon, South Korea, Aug. 2021 - Jun. 2022

Teaching Assistant of the Data Science Methodology class (CS564). Responsible for preparing and grading class assignments and assisting with administrative tasks.

#### Honors and Awards

# KAIST School of Humanities and Social Sciences Best Paper Award

Spring Semester, 2020

Received for the paper titled "How Granting Rights to AI and Robots Might Conflict with Human Rights."

# KAIST School of Computing Dean's List

Fall Semester, 2018

Received for outstanding academic achievement.

## Best Presentation Award Nov. 2018

Received at the International Conference on Signal Processing and Machine Learning 2018.

# KAIST Graduate/Undergraduate Research Project (GURP) Funding

Jan. 2018

Received KRW 8,000,000 (USD 6,700) for a research project on classifying emotion from raw speech data.

# **ACADEMIC SERVICES**

#### Reviewer

ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW)	2022
ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI) - Late Breaking Work	2022
We Robot Conference	2021

#### REFERENCES

## Prof. Meeyoung Cha, mcha@ibs.re.kr

Chief Investigator of the Data Science Group at the Institute for Basic Science (IBS) and Associate Professor at the KAIST School of Computing.

## Prof. Jiyoung Han, jiyoung.han@kaist.ac.kr

Assistant Professor at the KAIST Moon Soul Graduate School of Future Strategy.

#### Dr. Karandeep Singh, karandeepbrar@gmail.com

Senior Researcher at Data Science Group in the Institute for Basic Science (IBS).

# Nina Grgić-Hlača, nghlaca@mpi-sws.org

PhD Candidate at the Max Planck Institute for Software Systems (MPI-SWS) and the Max Planck Institute for Research on Collective Goods.